A Guide to the Douglas Summers Brown papers, 1936-1998
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Douglas Summers Brown papers, 1936-1998
Library of Virginia
37425
.9 cubic feet (2 boxes).
Douglas Summers Brown
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Douglas Summers Brown of Lynchburg, Virginia
Biographical Information
Douglas Summers Brown was born on 10 Jan. 1903 in Abingdon, Virginia. She attended Mary Baldwin College in Staunton, Virginia, and married Henry Dockery Brown, a Presbyterian minister, in 1926. Brown is an english and history teacher and author who has written several books on South Carolina and Virginia history, including A City Without Cobwebs: A History of Rock Hill, South Carolina (1954), Massanetta Minature: The Story of the Origin and Grown of the Synodical Training School of the Synod of Virginia (1964), A History of Lynchburg's Pioneer Quakers and Their Meeting House (c. 1936), The Catawba Indian: The People of the River (1966), and Historical and Biographical Sketches of Greensville County, Virginia, 1650-1967 (1968). Brown has also written articles for the Virginia Cavalcade, Sandlapper, Encyclopedia of American Quaker Genealogy, The Presbyterian Outlook, William and Mary Quarterly, Archeological Society of Virginia, Lynch's Ferry, and the Richmond Times-Dispatch.
Scope and Content
This collection documents Brown's work on regional histories of South Carolina and Virginia, Native Americans, and religious anecdotes and history. Included within the collection of literary manuscripts are biographies on Stephen Holston, Dolly Madison, Narcissa Tayloe Shawhan, George Allen Owl, John Woolman, Joseph Lafayette Meek, Wilbur Waters, and Charles Cummings. Also included are manscripts regarding the battle of the Crater (Petersburg, Va.), Catawba and Saponi Indians, history of Lynchburg (Va.) Quakers, and regional histories of Burke's Garden and Cedar Creek, Virginia. Some of the manuscripts include Brown's corrections and notations.
Contents List
- Biographical materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1994-1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Literary manuscripts, published
  - Aaron Burr, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Battle of the Crater, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cedar Creek Monthly Meeting and Its Meeting House, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Charles Cummings-The Fighting Parson of Sowthwest Virginia, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - A Circle Chairman's Prayer, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dolly Madison--Virginia Quakeress, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Folktales of the Catawba Indians, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Heraldic Artist--Fanny Setzer Faris, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - If You Must Be Your Own Doctor, 1942-1947 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Indian Who Went to London, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Let's Have a Talk About Church Extension, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Lynchburg's Quakers, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Major Woods, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Massanetta Miniature, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Men Who Would Not Be Put Upon, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous, 1944-1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Mrs. Cabell's Lynchburg, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - An Open Letter to All College Professors, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - The Saponi Indians--Their Town and Fort of 1708-1714, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Stephen Holston--Frontiersman, Adventurer, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - They Found City Shadows and Sent the Light, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - What Price Religious Freedom?--William Davis Pays, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Wilbur Waters of White Top Mountain, article, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Wilbur Waters of White Top Mountain, clippings, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Wings for the Soul, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 27)